<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | The Roth Lab</title>
    <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="rothmi12.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering the Phenylpropanoid Pathway for Disease Resistance</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/1_soybean_phenylpropanoid/</link>
      <pubDate>2022</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/1_soybean_phenylpropanoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most commercial soybean varieties are highly susceptible to &lt;em&gt;Sclerotinia sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt;, which causes the soybean disease known as Sclerotinia stem rot, or more commonly referred to as &amp;ldquo;white mold&amp;rdquo;. A recent study by Ranjan et al (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/pbi.13082&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;) showed that two recombinant inbred soybean lines from the same parentage respond differently when inoculated with &lt;em&gt;Sclerotinia sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt;, showing either susceptible or resistant phenotypes. Interestingly, the resistant soybean line developed a strong &amp;ldquo;red stem&amp;rdquo; phenotype (pictured above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing genetic responses between the two soybean lines indicated that a downregulation of genes in the phenylpropanoid pathway may be a key to mounting a resistance response. Additional metabolomics efforts showed that phenylpropanoid intermediates accumulated higher in the resistant line than the susceptible line. Finally, these phenylpropanoid intermediate compounds were shown to have anti-fungal activity, specifically targeting ergosterol biosynthesis.
&lt;img src=&#34;phenylpropanoid_pathway.png&#34; alt=&#34;Phenylpropanoid pathway, from Ranjan et al. 2019&#34;&gt;
My work is continuing on this project by identifying key genetic components of the phenylpropanoid pathway in soybean and using a gene silencing approach to knock down each phenylpropanoid gene candidate. Using this approach, I hope to validate the role of each gene in the phenylpropanoid pathway and identify targets that can be silenced to specifically lead to accumulating anti-fungal phenylpropanoid intermediates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Fungal-Nematode Interactions in Disease Complexes</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/5_fungal_nematode_interactions/</link>
      <pubDate>2021</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/5_fungal_nematode_interactions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Multiple disease complexes include plant pathogenic fungi and plant parasitic nematodes ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bsppjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1046/j.1365-3059.2002.00785.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Back et al. 2002&lt;/a&gt; ), including Verticillium dahliae with Pratylenchus nematodes in wilt disease of mint ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0211508&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wheeler et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt; ), Rhizoctonia solani and Ditylenchus dipsaci in sugar beet crown and root rot ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43229283&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hillnhütter et al. 2011&lt;/a&gt; ), and Fusarium solani and Meloidogyne incognita in root rot of lentil ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03235408.2018.1476116&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ahmed and Shahab 2018&lt;/a&gt; ). Similarly, it has been suggested that soybean sudden death syndrome (SDS) is a disease complex composed of &lt;em&gt;F. virguliforme&lt;/em&gt; and SCN, where SCN increases SDS synergistically with &lt;em&gt;F. virguliforme&lt;/em&gt; ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apsjournals.apsnet.org/doi/full/10.1094/PHYTO-02-19-0040-R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Roth et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt;; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apsjournals.apsnet.org/doi/abs/10.1094/PHYTO-96-0763&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Xing and Westphal 2013&lt;/a&gt; ). Similarly, &lt;em&gt;Macrophomina phaseolina&lt;/em&gt;, the causal agent of charcoal rot in soybean, is commonly found in the same fields as SCN and have a significant interaction on soybean yield ( 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://apsjournals.apsnet.org/doi/10.1094/PHYTO-03-19-0087-R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Lopez-Nicora et al. 2020&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the exact role of SCN in these disease complexes in soybean remain unknown. Some hypotheses include nematodes vectoring fungi into plants, nematodes creating wounds that are easier for fungi to colonize, and altering defense gene expression that benefits fungal invasion. Using fluorescently labelled strains of fungi and time-course microscopy, we are investigating the way fungi and nematodes interact outside of a plant host. Further experiments include the plant host will also help elucidate how pathogen interactions affect plant disease severity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Chestnut Microbiome for Causes of Graft Failure</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/6_chestnut_microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>2021</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/6_chestnut_microbiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chestnut species in the Castanea genus harbor a tremendous amount of genetic diversity among trees. This diversity contributes to differences in taste, size, quality, disease resistance, time to maturity, and yield across individual plants in an orchard, making it difficult to commercially farm. In apple, consistency in these qualities is achieved through grafting, which allows for clonal propagation of desirable apple varieties. Grafting success rates in apple are frequently greater than 90%, while chestnut grafting success rates are unacceptably low, frequently less than 50% and often as low as 10%. Chestnuts also harbor a great diversity of bacterial and fungal endophytes inside of the woody tissues. The goal of this project is to gain a deeper understanding of what fungal and bacterial species are present in chestnut trees before, during, and after grafting. We are using a high-throughput DNA sequencing approach to identify unique microbial DNA sequences, revealing the identity and abundance of all microbes in a single chestnut graft sample. We hypothesize that wounding and plant stress responses associated with the grafting process influence the abundance of specific microbes within a chestnut graft. This shift in abundance may allow one of these endophytes that are naturally present in a healthy chestnut tree to transition into a pathogenic phase, resulting in graft failure. With this information on the chestnut microbiome associated with grafting, we intend to test multiple biocontrol agents for their ability to suppress changes in the microbe abundance, ultimately improving grafting success rates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying virulence factors in Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/3_sclerotinia_effectors/</link>
      <pubDate>2020</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/3_sclerotinia_effectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microbes and plants interact by releasing recognizing different molecules. In plant pathology, pathogen-secreted molecules are often referred to as &amp;ldquo;effectors&amp;rdquo; because they effect plant physiology to establish an infection. However, pathogens also secrete factors that are not always classified as effectors, such as cell-wall degrading enzymes and secondary metabolites (reviewed in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.phyto.112408.132637&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stergiopoulos and de Wit 2009&lt;/a&gt;). Despite their categorization, the mechanisms by which pathogen-secreted molecules effect plants are very interesting to many researchers like me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a time-course transcriptome dataset, I have helped our research group identify candidate effector genes in &lt;em&gt;S. sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt;. Additionally, a CRISPR/Cas9 mediated transformation method developed by colleagues have facilitated the rapid, efficient transformation of &lt;em&gt;S. sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt;, allowing for characterization of genes involved in fungal development and pathogenicity on soybean and other plants. One effector that I am currently characterizes is particularly interesting because it appears to have two functions, able to act as a cell wall degrading enzyme &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; as an inducer of plant cell death.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-gene Mediated Susceptibility to White Mold in Soybean</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/2_soybean_rgene_susceptibility/</link>
      <pubDate>2020</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/2_soybean_rgene_susceptibility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The plant immune system is considered to be innate rather than adaptive. Part of this innate immune system is the presence of membrane bound proteins that can recognize specific molecules in the surrounding environment. These genes go by many different names, but are most commonly referred to as R-genes, where &amp;ldquo;R&amp;rdquo; stands for either &amp;ldquo;resistance&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;receptor&amp;rdquo;. When an R-gene recognizes certain molecules from plant pathogens, the R-gene can initiate defense signals to prevent the pathogen from infecting the plant. These defense signals often culminate in localized plant cell death - sacrificing part of the plant to save the whole organism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, some fungal plant pathogens specifically feed on dead plant tissue. Therefore, plant cell death is exactly what the fungal pathogen wants. Therefore, some necrotrophic fungi purposely release molecules that can be recognzied by R-genes, triggering localized plant cell death. This concept is referred to as the inverse gene-for-gene model (pictured above). Key examples of this have been shown in two different fungal diseases of wheat; tan spot (Ciuffetti et al 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03362.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt;), and Stagonospora nodorum blotch (Friesen and Faris 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/07060661003620896&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a bioinformatics approach, I analyzed the transcriptomes of susceptible and resistant soybean lines over time after inoculation with &lt;em&gt;Sclerotinia sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt;. I am specifically interested in identifying genes that showed opposite trends between the two lines in response to fungal infection. Genes that increased in the resistant line with a corresponding decrease in the susceptible line may indicate that gene&amp;rsquo;s role in resistance. Likewise, genes that increased in the susceptible line with a corresponding decrease in the resistant line may indicate that gene&amp;rsquo;s role in susceptibility. A graphical abstract of this concept can be found below.
&lt;img src=&#34;Sclerotinia-DEG-Graphical-Abstract.png&#34; alt=&#34;Graphical abstract for gene candidates involved in resistance to S. sclerotiorum. Made with biorender&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying genes based on this trend resulted in many gene candidates. To narrow down the search, I included additional criteria involving overall expression levels and statistics. These criteria included 1) overall average expression level &amp;gt; 1 rpkm, 2) expression present in both susceptible and resistant lines, and 3) no significant difference at 0 hpi. These criteria allowed us to identify genes that have strong expression levels (1) that change significantly in opposite directions (2), specifically in response to &lt;em&gt;S. sclerotiorum&lt;/em&gt; (3). This narrowed the list of candidates down to 1 gene, an R-gene that increased significantly in the susceptible line, but went down and stayed very low in the resistant line. Using a combination of reverse genetics approaches, virus-induced gene silencing, transient expression, and yeast two hybrid, I hope to validate the role of this R-gene in triggering plant cell death and also identify the cognate S. sclerotiorum protein that activates this susceptibility gene.
&lt;img src=&#34;GmEIX.png&#34; alt=&#34;Gene expression of the soybean R gene in susceptible and resistant lines in response to Sclerotinia sclerotiorum.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revealing Mechanisms of Induction of Soybean Sudden Death Syndrome</title>
      <link>rothmi12.github.io/project/4_sds_effectors/</link>
      <pubDate>2019</pubDate>
      <guid>rothmi12.github.io/project/4_sds_effectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microbes and plants interact by releasing recognizing different molecules. In plant pathology, pathogen-secreted molecules are often referred to as &amp;ldquo;effectors&amp;rdquo; because they effect plant physiology to establish an infection. However, pathogens also secrete factors that are not always classified as effectors, such as cell-wall degrading enzymes and secondary metabolites (reviewed in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.phyto.112408.132637&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stergiopoulos and de Wit 2009&lt;/a&gt;). Despite their categorization, the mechanisms by which pathogen-secreted molecules effect plants are very interesting to many researchers like me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fusarium virguliforme&lt;/em&gt;, causal agent of soybean sudden death syndrome (SDS) releases multiple effector proteins during infection (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0093667&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Abeysekara et al 2014&lt;/a&gt;). Two of these proteins, FvTox1 (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-12-10-0285&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brar et al. 2011&lt;/a&gt;) and FvNIS1 (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-09-15-0219-R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chang et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;), have been shown to play a role in chlorosis and necrosis, respectively. Using &lt;em&gt;Agrobacterium&lt;/em&gt;-mediated heterologous expression in tobacco, I was able to show that FvNIS1 (NF) still induces necrosis in tobacco similar to the positive control (R), while FvTox1 (TF) does not induce chlorosis in tobacco, similar to the empty vector control (EV). &lt;img src=&#34;SDS_agroinfiltration.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Agrobacterium infiltration of F. virguliforme effectors FvTox1 and FvNIS1&#34;&gt; These results suggest that FvNIS1 may target a pathway conserved across soybean and tobacco to induce necrosis, while FvTox1 may target a soybean-specific pathway to induce chlorosis. Future work will incude co-immunoprecipitation to identify FvTox1- and FvNIS1-interacting proteins, which may reveal mechanisms of SDS symptom development.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
